<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The impeachment and charge of Mr. Henry Hastings sonne to the Earle of Huntington concerning his manifold misdemeanors, the dangerous insurrections and tumults, occasioned by the said Mr. Hastings in the county of Leicester, to the disturbance and danger of the whole kingdome : which charge was drawn up by a select committee and by them presented to the Assembly of Lords, and an order from the Lords for the summoning of M. Hastings to his answer : also the substance of a speech spoken by the Earl of Pembrook before the committee, concerning an accommodation between the King and His Parliament, and the Parliaments command to all judges &amp;c.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B24577</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I94</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12273078</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12273078</idno>
            <idno type="VID">197362</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B24577)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 197362)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 245:E107, no 39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The impeachment and charge of Mr. Henry Hastings sonne to the Earle of Huntington concerning his manifold misdemeanors, the dangerous insurrections and tumults, occasioned by the said Mr. Hastings in the county of Leicester, to the disturbance and danger of the whole kingdome : which charge was drawn up by a select committee and by them presented to the Assembly of Lords, and an order from the Lords for the summoning of M. Hastings to his answer : also the substance of a speech spoken by the Earl of Pembrook before the committee, concerning an accommodation between the King and His Parliament, and the Parliaments command to all judges &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Warden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>... London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>July 22 [1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Loughborough, Henry Hastings, --  Baron, 1610-1667.</term>
               <term>Pembroke, Philip Herbert, --  Earl of, 1584-1650.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:197362:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IMPEACHMENT AND CHARGE OF Mr. <hi>Henry Haſtings</hi> Sonne to the Earle of <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> concerning his manifold Miſdemeanours, the dangerous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, and Tumults, occaſioned by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings</hi> in the County of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> to the diſturbance and danger of the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Which <hi>Charge</hi> was drawn up by a ſelect Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee and by them preſented to the Aſſembly of Lords; and an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the Lords, for the ſummoning of M. <hi>Haſtings</hi> to his Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſubſtance of a Speech ſpoken by the Earl of <hi>Pembrook</hi> before the <hi>Committee,</hi> concerning an Accommodation between the King and His <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> Command to all Judges &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ordered that this be printed and publiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hen. Elſing. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</p>
            <p>July 22. LONDON, Printed for <hi>Iohn Warden.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:197362:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:197362:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE IMPEACHMENT</hi> AND Charge of Mr. <hi>Henry Haſtings,</hi> Sonne to the Earl of <hi>Huntington.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe proceedings of Mr. <hi>Henry</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings <hi>in Lieceſterſhire</hi> hath bin ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, putting the inhabitants in a great fear and perplexity, he having bin at the Earl of <hi>Stamfords</hi> Houſe at <hi>Bradgate</hi> where the <hi>Magazine</hi> for that County re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, with ſome hundreds of men in Arms, &amp; at his comming thither, he made a Demand for the <hi>Magazine,</hi> and deſired that it might be delivered into his Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and keeping, and that the Charge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:197362:3"/> according to the Authority given him by his Majeſty might be delivered into his hands.</p>
            <p>But the Earl did withſtand his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and denyed that power which hee there made uſe of, and ſtill did reſerve the <hi>Militia</hi> in his own Cuſtody.</p>
            <p>Upon which denyall, M. <hi>Haſtings</hi> being very much moved, in his wrath and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler gave forth very inſolent and proud threats againſt the Earle, and all his Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and not only did ſtrive to ſtaine their ſpotleſſe Reputation with malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and moſt opprobrious tearms, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo proclaimed the Earl and all his follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers Traytors.</p>
            <p>The Report and Conſideration of theſe Out-rages by the ſaid <hi>Haſtings</hi> ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, took up each Houſe ſome time in debate, and occaſioned two Conference for the ſtopping and hindring of tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous meetings, both in that County and elſe-where.</p>
            <p>The Houſes being much moved at theſe troubls, took into their conſideration
<pb facs="tcp:197362:3"/> the ſtrength of the malignant Party with His Majeſty, and the oppoſition cauſed by them, to the great interruption of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentall Proceedings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt others concerning the late a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Mr. <hi>Haſtings</hi> in and about <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter:</hi> And after ſome debate thereupon, they appointed a Committee to draw up a Charge, againſt him and his Adherents. Upon the meeting of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, the Committee appointed, having prepared the Charge againſt Mr. <hi>Haſtings,</hi> according to the direction and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given them by the Houſe, it was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely read, and the Lords Houſe being compleated and ſetled, the ſaid Charge was ſent up unto them for their approbation alſo, with a Deſire of the ſaid Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Haſtings</hi> might bee forthwith proceeded aginſt, which was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to, and an Order iſſued forth for his ſummoning in to anſwer the ſame.</p>
            <p>On the 13. of <hi>JULY</hi> the Committees of both houſes being met about the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation
<pb facs="tcp:197362:4"/> between His Majeſty and His <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Pembroke</hi> made an excellent Speech; the ſubſtance whereof did diſcover and lay open the meanes for that moſt happy and deſired <hi>Union,</hi> and the happineſſe that would ariſe from that <hi>Conglatination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherupon the Committee taking into their ſerious conſideration, the beſt means for an Accommodation between the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> upon a Meſſage ſent to the Lords, there was a Conference.</p>
            <p>Where it was concluded, that a Select Committee of both Houſes ſhould meete the next morning, to conſider of thoſe <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moraes,</hi> which hindered that happy conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion, and to remove them if it were by any means poſſible.</p>
            <p>And upon their meeting the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, it was concluded, that the Earle of <hi>Holland</hi> ſhould preſent their Deſires to His Majeſty, who is now gone for the ſame Buſineſſe, whoſe Endeavours the Lord of his mercy bleſſe, for the benefit and peace of this Kingdom.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:197362:4"/>
            <head>An Order of the Lords and Commons, Aſſembled in Parliament.</head>
            <p>WHeras ſeverall Commiſſions of Array have lately iſsued out under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> into the ſeverall Counties of <hi>Leiceſter, Worceſter,</hi> and other Counties of this Realm, tending to the great danger of his Majeſty, and the diſturbance of the peace of this Kingdome: For the preventing thereof, and of the Execution, and iſsuing out of any ſuch Commiſſions for the time to come, It is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the Lords and Commons, That the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Juſtices of Aſſize, of the ſeverall Counties of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> bee required in their ſeverall Circuits, at the Aſſizes and great Seſſions to be next held for each County, within this Realm, and the Dominion of Wales, in open Court, and in their ſeverall Charges to be delivered to the Grand-Juries at the ſaid Aſſizes, openly to declare and publiſh, that the ſaid Lords and Commons have upon mature deliberation, Reſolved upon the queſtion, That the ſaid Commiſſions of Array are againſt Law, and againſt the Liberty and proper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of
<pb facs="tcp:197362:5"/> the Subject: And that all thoſe that are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in putting the ſame in execution, ſhall be eſteemed Diſturbers of the peace of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and Betrayers of the Liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng" subtype="order_to_print">
               <body>
                  <p>Ordered that this be printed and publiſhed,</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <closer>
               <signed> John Brown Cler. Par.<figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of a man's portrait</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:197362:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
